Guide to the Zenaida Gutiérrez-Vega Collection of José María Chacón y Calvo
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Zenaida Gutiérrez-Vega collection of José María Chacón y Calvo
1793-2007
1915-2007
GEN MSS 617
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
5.22
(13 boxes)
The collection consists of material created by or relating to José María Chacón y Calvo, which was accumulated by Zenaida Gutiérrez-Vega in the course of her research on the life and work of the Cuban-born literary critic and academic. Material includes original and copies of correspondence received by Chacón y Calvo from various Cuban, Spanish, and Latin American poets and writers; original manuscripts, typescripts, photocopies, and clippings of writings by Chacón y Calvo; an annotated typescript of Chacón y Calvo's diaries dating from 1917 to 1918; research files containing manuscripts, notes, letters, and printed material relating to other writers (possibly compiled by either Chacón y Calvo or Gutiérrez-Vega); original and photocopies of photographs of Chacón y Calvo; and other material.
Gutiérrez-Vega, Zenaida
Chacón y Calvo, José María, 1893-1969
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Carlos Ripoll, 2008.
Custodial History
Carlos Ripoll received the collection from Zenaida Gutiérrez-Vega.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 13: (computer disk): Restricted Fragile Material. Reference copies of electronic files are available. Consult Access Services for further information.
Jose Maria Chacon y Calvo (1898-1969)
José María Chacón y Calvo was a Cuban-born literary critic and academic. He focused on Cuban poetry, befriending and writing about a number of Cuban poets in Cuba and in Spain.
Chacón y Calvo was the subject of several books and articles edited or written by Zenaida Gutiérrez-Vega. Gutiérrez Vega (1924-2007?) was a Cuban-born academic who taught for nearly three decades at Hunter College, CUNY, and whose major subject of study was the life and work of José María Chacón y Calvo.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of material created by or relating to José María Chacón y Calvo, which was accumulated by Zenaida Gutiérrez-Vega in the course of her research on the life and work of the Cuban-born literary critic and academic. Material includes original and copies of correspondence received by Chacón y Calvo from various Cuban, Spanish, and Latin American poets and writers; original manuscripts, typescripts, photocopies, and clippings of writings by Chacón y Calvo; an annotated typescript of Chacón y Calvo's diaries dating from 1917 to 1918; research files containing manuscripts, notes, letters, and printed material relating to other writers (possibly compiled by either Chacón y Calvo or Gutiérrez-Vega); original and photocopies of photographs of Chacón y Calvo; and other material.
Correspondence includes unpublished letters and letters published in Epistolario Alfonso Reyes, José Ma. Chacón (1976), Fernando Ortiz en sus cartas a José Ma. Chacón (1914-1936, 1956) (1982), Corresponsales españoles de José Ma. Chacón (1986), and José María Chacón y Calvo: corresponsales cubanos (2006), all edited by Gutiérrez-Vega.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into three series: I. Photographs, Writings, and Other Papers, circa 1915-1969. II. Correspondence, circa 1910-2007. III. Research Material, 1793-1960s.
This organization is based on how the donor, who was the previous custodian of the collection, had organized the material.
Authors, Cuban -- 20th Century -- Archives; Cuban literature -- History and criticism; Cuban poetry -- History and criticism; Poets, Cuban -- 20th Century -- Archives; Born digital; Electronic documents; Chacón y Calvo, José María, 1893-1969; Gutiérrez-Vega, Zenaida; Lizaso, Félix, 1891-; Ortiz, Fernando, 1881-1969; Reyes, Alfonso, 1889-1959
- Photographs, Writings, and Other Papers, circa 1915-1969; Series I; 1.67; (4 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  The donor list describes the material in this series as: Fotos dedicadas a Chacón o firmadas; Fotos tomadas por Chacón o de él con otras personas; Ilustraciones para los libros que publicó Zenaida Gutiérrez Vega; Artículos publicados de Chacón; Escritos de Chacón.
  - Photographs - Chacón y Calvo, 2 (Box 1)
  - "Poesias de Maria Luisa Milanes", circa 1934 (Box 1)
  - Photographs - Chacón y Calvo (Box 1)
  - Chacón y Calvo manuscript (Box 1)
  - Ruben Dario (Box 1)
  - Chacón y Calvo photographs (Box 1)
  - "Various" (Box 2)
  - "Pedro Blanco, El Negrero" (Box 2)
  - Chacón y Calvo writings (Box 2)
  - Articles regarding Spanish Literature by Chacón y Calvo (Box 2)
  - Chacón y Calvo - "Diario en la Muerte de mi Madre" (Box 2)
  - Newspaper clippings, circa 1915 (Box 3)
  - Clippings regarding Spanish Literature (Box 3)
  - Chacón y Calvo writings (Box 3)
  - Newspaper clippings, circa 1930s (Box 3)
  - Chacón y Calvo - Clippings regarding Cuban literature (Box 3)
  - Cuba Internacional, magazine, 1969 August (Box 4)
  - Bio-bibliography of Chacón y Calvo (Box 4)
  - Chacón y Calvo - Clippings regarding Spanish Literature (Box 4)
  - "G. G. de Avellaneda" (Box 4)
  - "Julian del Casal" (Box 4)
  - Framed Chacón y Calvo stamp (Box 4)
  - Diaries of Chacón y Calvo, annotated typescript, circa 1917-1918 (Box 4)
- Correspondence, Series II; 2.92; (7 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged into five subseries: Spanish Correspondence, Cuban Correspondence, Unpublished Non-Cuban Correspondence, Unpublished Cuban Correspondence, and Other Correspondence.
  - Spanish Correspondence, circa 1910s-1950s
    The donor list describes this grouping of correspondence as: Files con cartas de los corresponsales españoles, que a continuación se relacionan, y fueron publicadas (excepto las que llevan asterisco*) en el libro Corresponsales españoles de José Ma. Chacón (1986).
    - Alberti, Rafael, circa 1920s (Box 5)
    - Alomar, Gabriel, circa 1930s (Box 5)
    - Araujo Costa, Luis*, circa 1930s (Box 5)
    - Azorín, circa 1950s (Box 5)
    - Ballesteros, Antonio, circa 1950s (Box 5)
    - Baroja, Pío*, circa 1930s (Box 5)
    - Bergamín, José*, circa 1930s (Box 5)
    - Bonilla y San Martín, Adolfo, circa 1920s (Box 5)
    - Calleja, Rafael, circa 1920s (Box 5)
    - Castro, Américo, circa 1920s (Box 5)
    - Díez-Canedo, Enrique, circa 1930s (Box 5)
    - Dalí, Salvador* (Box 5)
    - Diego, Gerardo, circa 1930s (Box 5)
    - Echegaray, Carmelo de, circa 1910s (Box 5)
    - Falla, Manuel de, circa 1920s (Box 5)
    - Fernández Almagro, Melchor, circa 1910s (Box 5)
    - Gailbrois de Ballesteros, Mercedes, circa 1920s (Box 5)
    - García Lorca, Federico, copies (Box 5)
    - García Solalinde, Antonio, circa 1920s (Box 5)
    - Gili Gaya, Samuel* (Box 5)
    - González de Amezúa, Agustín, circa 1950s (Box 5)
    - Guillén, Jorge (Box 5)
    - Jiménez, Juan Ramón*, circa 1950s (Box 5)
    - Lázaro, Ángel, circa 1950s (Box 5)
    - Marañón, Gregorio, circa 1950s (Box 5)
    - Marichalar, Antonio, circa 1930s (Box 5)
    - Menéndez Pelayo, Enrique, circa 1910s (Box 5)
    - Menéndez Pidal, Ramón, circa 1950s (Box 5)
    - Navarro Tomás, Tomás, circa 1920s (Box 5)
    - Oliver Belmás, Antonio, circa 1930s (Box 5)
    - Ors, Eugenio d', circa 1930s (Box 5)
    - Ots, José María, circa 1920s (Box 5)
    - Ríos, Blanca de los, circa 1920s (Box 5)
    - Rubio, Antonio, circa 1930s (Box 5)
    - Saínz Rodríguez, Pedro (Box 5)
    - Sánchez Albornoz, Claudio (Box 5)
    - Serna, Ramón de la, circa 1930s (Box 5)
    - Serís, Homero*, circa 1930s (Box 5)
    - Loose papers (Box 5)
  - Cuban Correspondence, circa 1910s-1970s
    The donor list describes this grouping of correspondence as: Files con las cartas de los corresponsales cubanos, que a continuación se relacionan, y fueron publicadas en el libro José María Chacón y Calvo: corresponsales cubanos (2006).
    - Acosta, Agustín, circa 1930s-1970s; 2 (Box 6)
    - Armas, José de, circa 1910s (Box 6)
    - Ballagas, Emilio, circa 1930s (Box 6)
    - Boti, Regino E., circa 1920s (Box 6)
    - Carbonell, Miguel Ángel, circa 1950s (Box 6)
    - Castillo de González, Aurelia, circa 1910s (Box 6)
    - Catalá, Ramón A, circa 1920s (Box 6)
    - Ferrara, Orestes, circa 1950s (Box 6)
    - Giberga, Eliseo, circa 1910s (Box 6)
    - Hernández Catá, Alfonso, circa 1910s (Box 6)
    - Loynaz, Dulce María (Box 6)
    - Mañach, Jorge, circa 1920s (Box 6)
    - Montoro, Rafael, circa 1930s (Box 6)
    - Pérez de Zambrana, Luisa (Box 6)
    - Pichardo Moya, Felipe, circa 1910s (Box 6)
    - Ramos, José Antonio, circa 1910s (Box 6)
    - Remos, Juan J., circa 1915-1950s (Box 6)
    - Rodríguez, Luis Felipe, circa 1920s (Box 6)
    - Sanguily, Manuel, circa 1910s (Box 6)
    - Torriente y Peraza, Cosme de la, circa 1920s-1930s (Box 6)
    - Varona, Enrique José, circa 1910s-1920s (Box 6)
    - Vitier, Medardo, circa 1930s (Box 6)
  - Unpublished Non-Cuban Correspondence, circa 1910s-1950s
    The donor list describes this grouping of correspondence as: Files con las cartas de corresponsales de otros países que a continuación se relacionan, que NO han sido publicadas.
    - Araujo-Costa, Luis, circa 1930s (Box 7)
    - Blanco-Fombona, Rufino, circa 1920s (Box 7)
    - Castro Leal, Antonio, circa 1910s (Box 7)
    - Contreras, Francisco, circa 1920s (Box 7)
    - Farinelli, Arturo (Box 7)
    - Fitzmaurice-Kelly, Jaime, circa 1910s (Box 7)
    - González Martínez, Enrique, circa 1910s (Box 7)
    - Gómez Restrepo, Antonio, circa 1930s (Box 7)
    - Gutiérrez, Aostria, circa 1920s (Box 7)
    - Henríquez Ureña, Max, circa 1910s (Box 7)
    - Henríquez Ureña, Pedro, 2 (Box 7)
    - Hernández, Manuel, circa 1950s (Box 7)
    - Icaza, Francisco, circa 1920s (Box 7)
    - Mistral, Gabriela (Box 7)
    - Ocampo, Victoria (Box 7)
    - Rojas, Ricardo, circa 1930s (Box 8)
    - Sanín Cano, Baldomero, circa 1950s (Box 8)
    - Valle-Arizpe, Artemio de, circa 1920s (Box 8)
    - Vossler, Karl, circa 1930s (Box 8)
    - Various (Box 8)
      This folder includes correspondence from José de la Riva Agüero (Perú), Artemio de Valle-Arizpe (México), Rafael Estrada (Costa Rica), Luis Alberto Sánchez (Perú), Nicolás Rangel (México) and Ventura García Calderón (Perú).
  - Unpublished Cuban Correspondence, circa 1910s-2007
    The donor list describes this grouping of correspondence as: Files con las cartas de corresponsales cubanos NO publicadas. El asterisco indica que las cartas y la presentación de los autores están digitalizadas en el Disco Duro (CorresponsalesCubanosNuevos.doc.) y en un Drive que conservo, como para un nuevo libro. El número que sigue a cada autor es el de las páginas que ocupa en lo digitalizado, y sirve para dar una idea de la extensión del material.
    - *Aramburo y Machado, Mariano 60, circa 1910s-1920s (Box 8)
    - Armas, Susini de, circa 1920s-2007 (Box 8)
    - *Baralt, Luis 35, circa 1910s (Box 8)
    - *Barraqué, Jesús María 4, circa 1920s-1930s (Box 8)
    - *Borrero, Dulce María 7 (Box 8)
    - *Byrne, Bonifacio 10, circa 1910s (Box 8)
    - *Carpentier, Alejo 2 (Box 8)
    - Castellanos, José R. (Box 8)
    - *Castellanos, Francisco José 49, circa 1910s (Box 8)
    - *Conangla Fontanilles, José 6 (Box 8)
    - *Cortina, José Manuel 2, circa 1920s (Box 8)
    - Cruz, Manuel de la, circa 1920s (Box 8)
    - Dihigo, Ernesto, circa 1920s (Box 8)
    - *Dihigo, Juan Miguel 8, circa 1920s (Box 8)
    - *Entralgo, Elías 16, circa 1950s (Box 8)
    - *Escoto, José Agustín, circa 1910s (Box 8)
    - *Fernández de Castro, José Antonio 17, circa 1930s (Box 8)
    - *Florit, Eugenio 3, circa 1930s (Box 8)
    - *González del Valle, Francisco 6 (Box 8)
    - *González Lanuza, José Antonio 9, circa 1910s (Box 8)
    - Guerra Flores, José (Box 8)
    - Iraizoz, Antonio (Box 8)
    - Labrador Ruiz, Enrique, circa 1936 (Box 8)
    - *Loynaz, Enrique 55 (Box 9)
    - *León, José de la Luz 22, circa 1930s (Box 9)
    - Lles y Berdayes, Fernando, circa 1920s (Box 9)
    - *Marinello, Juan 11, circa 1920s (Box 9)
    - Massip, Salvador, circa 1930s (Box 9)
    - Maza Ledesma, Enrique, circa 1916 (Box 9)
    - *Novás Calvo, Lino 20, circa 1930s (Box 9)
    - *Pichardo, Manuel Serafín 25, circa 1930s (Box 9)
    - *Pita Rodríguez, Félix 6, circa 1930s (Box 9)
    - *Portell-Vilá, Herminio 14, circa 1930s (Box 9)
    - Rodríguez de Tio, Lola, circa 1910s (Box 9)
    - Rodríguez-Embil, Luis, circa 1910s-1920s (Box 9)
    - Rubinos, José, circa 1930s (Box 9)
    - Sánchez de Bustamante y Montoro, Antonio, circa 1930s (Box 9)
    - *Sánchez Galarraga, Gustavo, circa 1930s (Box 10)
      The donor list notes the following about this file: no encuentro el diskette con la trascripción de los originales; hay mecanuscrito al que le he hecho un diskette que le copio a su sobrino Jorge Sánchez Galarraga.
    - Santovenia, Emeterio, circa 1930s- (Box 10)
    - *Trelles, Carlos M. 20, circa 1917 (Box 10)
    - *Varela Zequeira, José 7 (Box 10)
    - Villar Buceta, María (Box 10)
  - Other Correspondence, circa 1920s-1960s
    - Acosta, Agustín, circa 1950s-1960s; 2 (Box 10)
      The donor list notes the following about this file: Files con cartas no publicadas de Chacón a Agustín Acosta
    - Estalella, Ramón, circa 1940s-1960s (Box 10)
    - Lizaso, Felix, circa 1960s; 2 (Box 11)
    - Ortiz, Fernando, circa 1920s- (Box 11)
      The donor list notes the following about this file: Files con las cartas de Fernando Ortiz publicadas en el libro Fernando Ortiz en sus cartas a José Ma. Chacón (1982).
    - Reyes, Alfonso, circa 1920s (Box 11)
      The donor list notes the following about this file: Files con las cartas de Alfonso Reyes, publicadas en el libro Epistolario Alfonso Reyes, José Ma Chacón (1976).
- Reasearch Material, circa 1793-1960s; Series III; 0.42; (1 box)
  - El Dos de Mayo, 1821 (Box 12)
  - Shield of Cuba (Box 12)
  - Manuel de la Cruz, circa 1890s (Box 12)
    Includes La Revolucion Cubana y La Raza de Color (Apuntes y Datos) Por Un Cubano Sin Odios (1895).
  - Various poems - Duque de Rivas, Domingo del Monte and others (Box 12)
  - Gustavo Sánchez Galarraga (Box 12)
  - Don José Antonio Iznaga y Borrell, circa 1820s (Box 12)
  - Máximo Gómez, circa 1870s (Box 12)
  - Homenaje a Fermin Valdes Dominguez, circa 1890 (Box 12)
  - Antonio López de Santa-Ana, Cuban proclamation (Box 12)
  - Breve Descripcion del Mundo en Verso, 1793 (Box 12)
  - Enrique José Varona - M. de la Cruz (Box 12)
  - Various (Box 12)
  - "Corresponsales Espanoles de José M. Chacón", photocopy (Box 12)
  - "Félix Lizaso y José María Chacón y Calvo. Medio siglode cultura cubana (1916-1966)", photocopy, 2 (Box 12)
- Restricted Fragile, 0.21; (1 box)
  - Computer disk (20080513-16040.0001) (Box 13)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Box 13: (computer disk): Restricted Fragile Material. Reference copies of electronic files are available. Consult Access Services for further information.